So last week we spoke about parenting.
This week we're going to be coming to
the subject of marriage. Now just so
we're clear, Roy believes in marriage
before having kids and being a parent.
Uh but we we've done them in reverse. Uh
but every few years I I feel compelled
as a pastor, whether foolishly or
wisely. You you you can be the judge of
that. I feel compelled to talk about
topics like parenting, like marriage and
like relationships. Uh because these
these things are so essential to
understanding uh the Bible and the
kingdom and our place in God's
redemptive story that to neglect these
areas, to neglect thinking and preaching
on marriage and parenting and
relationships
uh is to the detriment of our souls.
Now, it's always risky when you do
sermons on parenting and on marriage
that there's people who don't fit those
categories and they feel singled out and
they they they sort of are multiplied in
their affliction of wanting a wife or
wanting a husband and still are single
and looking. Now, to those I I want to
say that this isn't a personal attack.
It's nothing like that. Uh, Proverbs are
just so [snorts] family marriage
centered that it's hard to get around
them when you're preaching in Proverbs.
So, uh, there are more than a handful of
people in this church that are not
married or cannot have kids and and
it's, uh, to you that I I just want to
express the love uh, and the the
shephering that the pastors and elders
have for you uh, in this church. We we
love those of you who don't fit uh,
what's called the norm. Right? There are
exceptions to the norm. Normally, people
leave their father and mother, hold fast
to their spouse, and have children. Uh
but it's not always the case in God's
providence or special gifting. Uh that
that's always the case. And so marriage
isn't everything. Uh but it is central
to the purpose and plans of God in this
world. And that's why the Bible so
frequently addresses children and
marriage ultimately in heaven. That is
where the the ultimate marriage between
Christ and his bride will be had. There
will be no earthly marriages that we
experience in heaven, but only the
perfect marriage of the bride of Christ
to her husband Jesus. And it's in that
hope that we all rejoice and look
forward to as fellow believers. Amen.
Amen. So, if you are married this
morning, this is going to be more of a
uh here's what to strive for in marriage
as uh as the excellent wife is portrayed
as a as um here's what to avoid as a
quarrelome wife is portrayed as a
husband. Here's what to strive for and
here's what to avoid in marriage. Right?
So, if you're married, that's sort of a
sermon for you this morning. If you're
single, here's the people that you need
to watch out for. Uh don't don't go
after someone like this. uh but do go
after someone like this. So that's how I
want to frame this sermon so that it's
applicable to everyone here this
morning. Um let's pray because I
certainly need prayer and then we will
get into God's word. Father, we thank
you uh for Christ, our great bridegroom
who uh has come from heaven to seek and
to save
his eternal bride that he set his sights
upon even before we were born. Even
before the creation of the world, Christ
had a mission to come and to redeem his
precious people,
his holy sheep that are predestined to
be in him. Ephesians 1.
And we thank you for that redemption and
that salvation that we have. And we
thank you that that picture of the
gospel is seen in husbands and wives
laying down their lives for the for the
sake of Christ and the other person.
Father, may my words be a pleasing aroma
in your sight. And may they be a balm
and an ointment to those who need to
hear. I pray that you would convict
those who need conviction this morning.
I pray you would give the right amount
of burden and weight on those who need
to have that. I pray the spirit would do
his work through his word and I'm simply
the instrument by which that comes.
Ultimately we pray you would show us
Christ in Jesus name. Amen.
The Hebrew word for glory in the Bible
means heavy. Heavy. It's the Hebrew word
cavode uh which refers to heaviness or
or weight or glory. When God shows his
glory in the Bible when when people are
hit with the glory of God, they fall
down because it's heavy, it's full, it's
weighty. So in the Bible, we see God
literally showing his presence, his
glory, his substance, his glory. And we
spoke a little bit last week about the
the weight of bearing children, the
heavy burden, but the good burden that
is. Uh this week is much the same.
Marriage is a glorious weight that we
are to bear in order to reflect the
glory of God. God's glory is seen first
fundamentally in our personhood as male
and female. He made us in his image to
reflect his glory.
But on top of that, it's also seen in
the roles of men and women as they come
together in marriage to display the
husband and the wife and their
respective glories. When they come
together in marriage and they play the
roles that the Bible tells for them to
play, uh they multiply that glory of God
that they already had as male and
female, but now they do it in a way that
reflects Christ and the church, Jesus
and his bride.
But maybe as you've read through the
Bible and specifically the Proverbs,
maybe you've never noticed that when the
Bible addresses the topic of marriage,
it seemingly has much more to say to
women than it does to men. I don't know
if you've ever noticed that, but when
the Bible addresses the topic of
marriage, or specifically the Proverbs,
it seems to appeal predominantly to the
character of women and what women are
like in marriage than it [snorts] does
men. It talks about the quarrelome wife.
talks about, you know, living in a
rooftop is better than living with a
contentious woman and so forth. And
maybe you're tempted to go, hey, hey,
what's the deal here, God? Why is it so
woman centric? Well, it's actually not.
Um, it's not to say that the Bible
favors men over women, or it's not that
the Bible assumes women need more
correction than men. Not the case. The
reason obviously is twofold. First, the
book of Proverbs is addressed to sons.
It's addressed to young men who are
looking looking for a virtuous woman, a
virtuous wife. And in order to know what
the virtuous woman looks like, you also
have to compare her to the contentious
woman, to the to the wife that you
should be avoiding.
The other reason is that the Bible
recognizes, as do many of the proverbs,
that a woman's uh glory and role in this
world is chiefly, not exclusively, but
chiefly seen as a homemaker, as a woman
who serves her home, a woman whose heart
is for her home, her family.
In fact, I'm told that it's only at a
few weeks gestation, maybe six or seven
weeks. I think doctors say that a a tiny
baby girl inside of her mother's womb
has the early early stages, the
beginning parts of what will become a
uterus. The early beginning stages of a
tiny baby girl in her mother's womb has
the earliest signs of what will be the
home of her future children.
A woman is quite literally someone who
is made with a home inside of her.
Someone who was literally designed to be
a home maker. In fact, uh I like this
quote. Someone said the very first home
every single person in this room ever
lived in was the home of their mother's
womb.
A woman simply is a homemaker. She is
made with a home inside of her. This
says nothing against those who by
gifting or by providence are unmarried
or maybe cannot bear children here this
morning.
In other words, because you're not
married or maybe you struggle to uh have
children as a woman doesn't make your
glory any less true or substantial. You
still have full glory of the glory and
image of God as a woman, as a homemaker.
Because we're talking about the general
pattern of the world, the way that it
normally goes, right? The way that it
normally tends to go is that a woman's
chief glory and her contribution to the
kingdom of God is seen in her making of
disciples of little heart, shaping
immortal souls and her service to the
home. Now again, that's not to say that
women can't contribute in other areas
like outside the home. It's not to say
they can't work outside the home. But
the way the Bible talks about this in so
far as her priority is first for her
home. Everything she does is geared
towards serving her home, loving her
home as a homemaker. That is where her
principled glory shines. This is why
Paul, for instance, this is Paul's words
in Titus chapter 2. Hans's going to get
there and he he may do a whole sermon on
this. So, stay tuned for that. Titus 2,
Paul says, 'Older women are to be
teaching younger women what it means to
be dignified, godly, submissive, and
self-controlled workers of the home.
Workers of the home. Now, maybe we don't
agree with that this morning, or maybe
you don't agree with that point. Maybe
you think that this is uh sort of
outdated, it's sexist, or that the Bible
needs far more nuance and careful
wording with how it talks about these
things. But the response the Bible has
always given to modern-day critics and
uh let's say the the purplehead people
of this world who hate the idea of women
serving in the in the home uh is that
the Bible simply doesn't care what man's
opinion thinks of it. The Bible is God's
word. It simply doesn't cater to human
opinions. The Bible is God's uh loving,
objective, authoritative word and it
advocates for the glory and the value of
women. And therefore, in the spirit of
all humility because the Bible doesn't
care about offending modern
sensibilities and human opinions, then
neither should we.
We shouldn't care because firstly, the
Bible's never really been popular with
the world up until 2026. And even in
2026, people still don't like what the
Bible has to say. So, uh, my my opinion
is why accommodate to the minds of those
who are hostile to the things of God.
Anyway, and let me also remind you that
the Bible uh deals with men and how
foolish men are in the first nine
chapters uh and and the stupidity and
the dumbness of what men are like when
it comes to going after contentious
women. And so the Bible is not really
that heavy-handed when it comes to
women. It speaks to both men and women
and their respective glories. The glory
of men, the glory of women. Putting this
all together, that's why God gave us
Proverbs. So all that to say, Proverbs
18:22, if you have your Bibles, Proverbs
18:22 is the launching text for
marriage. The main point we're going to
see as we come to uh marriage in the
proverbs is that marriage is a glorious
gift that can either multiply your joy
or magnify your grief. Marriage is a
glorious gift that can either multiply
your joy or magnify your grief depending
on the kind of person you are in
marriage. Your choice is up to you. What
kind of a husband are you going to be?
What kind of a wife do you want to be?
What kind if you're single, what kind of
a person are you looking for?
What kind of a spouse do you want to
avoid? All of this is addressed in the
proverbs. So, Proverbs 18, listen to
this text, very famous proverb,
verse 22, it says this, "He who finds a
wife finds a good thing and obtains
favor from the Lord." The Bible has
always spoken and will always speak
highly of the covenant of marriage.
Marriage according to the Bible is not
just a good thing. It's not just a God
thing. It is the best thing for a human
society and civilization
to flourish, to go forth, to multiply,
to have dominion. In fact, we remember
that when God created the world in in
six literal days of speaking, there was
a a cadence to the creation. There was a
a rhythm that you can pick it up. Even
in the Hebrew, there's the rhythm. But
even in English translations, you can
kind of see a pattern in creation. In
Genesis 1, you know, God created this
and this and this and it was good. And
God created this and then this and this
and it was good. And God created this
and this and this and it was good.
There's sort of this this rhythm, this
this predictability that's seen on the
pages of creation.
But then when you get to Genesis 2 and
you you zero in on that creation in
Genesis 1, Genesis 2 is a more detailed
account of what you just read in Genesis
1, we see there's there's a rhythm that
gets interrupted.
There's there's sort of this on the
record player. It's like, well, hang on
a minute. There's something Genesis
21:18 that's now not good. God blesses
creation, calls it good. It's good. It's
good. Genesis 2:18. Now, it's not good.
Something's not good in creation. Then
the Lord God said, "It's not good that
man should be alone. So, I will make a
helper fit
for him." He comes to man and he
communicates, "Humanity being in a state
of isolation
is a status that is incompleted. It's
not the way that man was designed to
remain." Adam had a mission. Adam had a
purpose and assignment that he needed to
do. And he could not do that without a
wife, without a helper helping him
cultivate, helping him build, helping
him multiply that image and that glory
of God in the world. And so we know the
text, it's very famous text, Genesis
2:21. So the Lord God caused a deep
sleep to fall upon the man, and while he
slept, he took one of his ribs, closed
up its place with flesh, and the rib
that the Lord God had taken from the
man, he made into a woman and brought
her to the man. He He takes the rib
because the woman is his side partner,
right? Not from his feet so that he
could trample over her. No, no, no. She
is equal in glory and beauty and the
image of God. And therefore, she is his
helper who who is from the side of him,
literally from his side. And so when God
creates woman, he brings her to the man.
This at last, and this is this is Adam's
words, right? This is the the first
words of humanity spoken on the pages of
of the Bibles about marriage. This at
last is bone of my bone, flesh of my
flesh. She shall be called woman because
she was taken out of man.
Now, many have noted here, and I I think
it's significant for us to note the
Bible when uh Adam's using this
language, bone of my bone, flesh of my
flesh. Adam's using what could be
classified as a Hebrew superlative. It's
a big fancy word. You remember
superlatives back in your schooling
days. Superlative was sort of a way to
describe the highest degree of a
particular thing, right? So in English
we have superlatives. We say things like
good, better,
best. So best is the superlative in that
sentence. We have big, bigger,
>> biggest. Yeah. Yeah. I knew you guys
could pass grade four. All right. Great.
Greater
>> greatest. Okay. So we're all on the same
page. So in Hebrew, what they would do
to to take a word and make it a
superlative, they would put the word of,
right? They would put the word of in the
sentence. So like if the word's big,
they would say big of the bigs, right?
Of all the bigs, this is the biggest,
right? Great of the greats. Of all the
greats, this is the the greatest. It's
the highest. You've actually seen this
form of Hebrew superlative in your
Bible. You may not have recognized, but
we often or the Bible actually often
calls Jesus the King of Kings, right?
He's the Lord of Lords. Out of all the
kings, all the lords, he's the greatest.
He's the highest of those lords. One of
the most common superlatives in the Old
Testament is the Holy of Holies.
sometimes translated as the most holy
place. Uh there's a book in the Bible
called the Song of Songs, the Song of
Songs. Out of all the songs, uh this
seems to be in Solomon's mind the
greatest. It's the best song. It's the
loveliest song. And ironically, it's a
song all about the covenant of marriage.
And so, we see what Adam is doing now in
Genesis when when Eve is brought to the
man. This this at last is bone of all my
bones. Right? This is flesh of all my
flesh. There's nothing greater. There's
nothing more lovely than this earthly
object of of Adam's greatest delight.
Adam delights in his wife. And he says
she is the the best version of him.
She's she makes her husband shine. She
makes her husband shine. The way that
Paul says this in 1 Corinthians 11, the
New Testament, Paul says, "Woman is the
glory of man. Woman's the glory of man."
And since Paul in that passage says that
man is the glory of God,
what Paul says that is that woman is
literally the glory of the glory. Man's
the glory of God, but woman's the glory
of man. And therefore, she is glory
glorified. She's glory of the glory. You
think of a tree. A tree is glorious in
the way that it's strong. Its trunk is
big and it has these giant leaves.
But what makes the tree glorious is if
there's beautiful purple or pink flowers
or whatever kind of beautifying of the
tree there is, those flowers are the
glory of what's already glorious. Right?
If you think of glory as that which
emanates or or radiates,
Paul says that woman is the crown of
creation. If humanity is the pinnacle,
woman is the crown of that pinnacle. She
is his glory.
The way that the proverbs put puts this
in proverbs 12, Proverbs 12:4 says that
an excellent wife is the crown of her
husband. She makes her husband shine. An
excellent wife is the crown of a
husband, but she who brings shame is
like rottness
to his bones.
I don't know if we realize how much a
woman, a wife profoundly affects
a husband's soul.
I don't think women realize, or maybe
they do, how much
powerful effect they can have on a home
and on a a man's heart, either for good
or for evil.
It's been said that even the strongest
man in this world, the strongest male
you can think of, can be eaten away from
the inside out from a quarrelome wife.
In fact, Solomon says she is like cancer
to his bones, rottness to his bones,
literally like bone cancer.
At the same time, the weakest man in the
world, the the most futile man who walks
can walk like a king if his wife is an
excellent wife. If she's a what the
proverbs say, Proverbs 31 woman. That's
the effect that women can have on the
heart of their home. Now, just so we
know, Proverbs 31 is going to be sort of
the final sermon in this series, and we
don't have too many more to go, to be
honest. So, uh, ladies, if you can hold
out till then, uh, gentlemen, you're
looking for an excellent wife, hold out
till then. I will do a sermon devoted to
the Proverbs 31 wife. And I think I
think it'll be encouraging. Um, I'm
excited to preach it. But if you were to
go home today and sort of look at the
qualities of the Proverbs 31 woman, I
won't get you to turn there. It's a bit
of a lengthy passage. Uh but basically
it says she's trustworthy, she's
diligent, she's resourceful, she's
hardworking, she's industrious, she's
perceptive, skilled, kind, caring, uh
strong, dignified, courageous, wise,
godly, respected, admired, praiseworthy,
and above all, you can see the labor of
her hands because her hands work for the
home. She labors for the heart of her
home. Everything she does is others
centered. It's not self-centered. It's
others focused.
And because her conduct, her beauty, and
her praise is geared toward her home and
her husband,
she makes her husband shine. There's
verse 23 in Proverbs 31, sort of the
center point of that entire passage, and
it's, you know, his reputation is known
at the city gates because of his his
wife. She makes his ministry. She makes
his business. She makes his mission, his
reputation
shine. Like the crown of a king living
in Israel, wives have a profoundly
powerful effect on their husband's wife.
She is the crown of her husband.
But of course, the opposite's true.
Solomon's sons don't know what the
excellent wife's like until they know
what the quarrelome wife is like. And
that's why you have uh better to live in
the wilderness. Proverbs 21:19. This is
the quarrelome wife. Now, better to live
in the wilderness than with a
contentious and angry woman in the home.
It's also true of men. It's better to
live in the wilderness than with a
contentious man. But the proverb focuses
on a woman here. A contentious woman
will drive a man, Solomon says, into the
harsh, bitter elements with snakes,
spiders, scorpions, wolves, bears,
lions, and fierce predators. a lack of
resources, no food, no water, 40°ree
heat. Better to be there living with no
roof than under a roof comfortably in a
home with a contentious woman. Better to
be in that kind of environment than with
a woman who is bitter and nagging and
contentious. Or at best, maybe not in
the howling wilderness, but the other
famous proverb we know, Proverbs 21:9,
better to live in the corner of a
housetop than in a house with a
quarrelome wife. So again, rooftops in
these days were open, flat, no roof on
top of them. They were exposed to the
elements. There was no shade, no
shelter, no protection from the sun, the
rain or anything like that. So it's
better to live up there being rained
upon than in a bed with a combative
wife. Why? Because Proverbs 27:15
says, "A quarrelome wife and a constant
drip are both alike." A a quarrelome
wife and a constant drip are both alike.
There is no difference Solomon says
between uh the constant drip drip drip
drip drip drip drip drip drip drip. It
gets annoying. Drip drip drip day after
day after day after day after day after
day.
and a wife who's contentious.
Which doesn't sound too bad at first
until you realize that if you get enough
water to drip consistently for a long
enough period of time on one location,
you can do great damage. You can do
great damage. You can carve out
something potentially as big as
a canyon.
That's how painful it is to be with a
man or a woman, but we're talking about
women in this instance.
who don't fear God, who don't serve
their home, who don't honor their
husbands, and who lives for themselves.
Now, again, ladies, if you're sitting
there feeling convicted or what not,
I hope that's the Holy Spirit. I hope
it's nothing I've said,
but if you're asking yourself, what kind
of a a woman would be contentious? What
are the qualities of a contentious woman
other than calling her contentious?
There's a a neat little trick you can do
when you go to Proverbs 31 later today.
You just sort of flip it on its head.
All the qualities that are the virtuous
and excellent wife, you sort of just
flip them on their head and look at the
inverse of them. So you take the
qualities and the features and you
simply flip them to read like this. A
quarrelome wife is easily found. She's
common. She's more costly than jewels.
The heart of her husband does not trust
in her, but he suffers great loss. She
does him harm and not good all the days
of her life. She neglects what is hers
to steward and to work. She works with
reluctant hands. She consumes what
others provide and she provides little
for her home. She rises late and she
sleeps early. She leaves needs unmet.
Her home fills the absence of her care.
She acts without foresight and weakness
is what she touches. She's clothed not
with strength but with instability. She
fears the future. She spreads that fear
within her walls. She opens her mouth
not with wisdom but bitterness,
sharpness, angers on her tongue. She
doesn't watch over the ways of her home.
She eats the bread of idleness. Her home
feels the strain of her instability.
Charm becomes manipulation. Her beauty
is vain. And she is a woman who does not
fear the Lord. and she will not be
praised. In fact, her works condemn her
in the gates.
It's a it's a haunting image really when
you think about a woman like that. It's
a powerful description of the quarrelome
wife.
It goes to prove the power of women and
their ability to either build up or tear
down a home. Proverbs 14:1, "The wise
woman builds her house, but the foolish
tears it down."
the foolish tears down her home. And
what's interesting to note is if you go
to Proverbs 27 again, the the constant
drip and the woman who's contentious,
the next verse, Proverbs 27:15 says, "A
quarrelome wife and a constant drip are
both alike." The next verse says, "To
restrain her is like restraining the
wind or grasping oil in one's right
hand." You ever tried to pour oil and
just do this without it spilling out?
It's impossible. Have you ever gone
outside on a windy day and said, "Stop."
It's not going to work. It's impossible.
You can't restrain the wind. And Solomon
says, "You got better chance at
restraining the wind or holding oil than
you do it controlling the contentious
woman." And so, the good news is that
although you can't control how your
spouse acts and reacts,
God can. You can't change the heart of
someone who is contentious. But God can
and he does through his word. Ladies,
the good news is that Jesus can and cha
does change hearts and homes more and
more into his image. We're all works of
progress. We're all being worked upon by
the spirit day after day to be conformed
to his image. And it begins by going to
his word, by recognizing your sins,
living and confessing your sins, and
living under the authority of Jesus.
It means embracing your calling in the
home cheerfully and faithfully, knowing
you're making the eternal difference of
shaping immortal souls to the glory of
God. There is great hope to be had in
the person and work of Jesus Christ. And
it begins by trusting and obeying his
word and how he tells us to live.
Now, a good wife also needs the other
half, which is the good husband.
Husbands thought they were getting out
of the sermon today, but they're not.
There is, in fact, an old saying that
goes, "Heavy is the head that wears the
crown." That's not in the Bible, but
it's an old saying nonetheless. I think
it might be Shakespeare.
A good crown demands
responsibility. A good crown demands a
good head. A husband doesn't get a crown
for no reason. What the proverbs
actually assume when it comes to the
excellent wife is that there is a man
who is leading the wife into excellency,
leading and teaching and guiding and
shaping his wife more and more into that
excellent woman. This is a mutual
marriage. This is a complimentary
relationship.
Which means men that your wife is a
reflection of your leadership. She's a
reflection of your authority. She's a
reflection of your shephering. And how
you treat your wife in the home
determines the kind of home you will
have. The way in which you treat your
wife in the home determines the kind of
home you're going to have. 1 Peter
chapter 3 gives the command to husbands
to honor their wives, to live with them
in an understanding way, and to treat
them as the weaker vessel. That is that
men are naturally designed to be the
protector of their wives.
And it also means that men are called to
be stronger [snorts] and use that
strength to defend and protect their
wives. It means that if the husband and
wife for whatever reason got into a cage
match,
the husband's going to win that. The
husband's going to win because men are
designed to be physically stronger. Now,
there are some, again, exceptions to the
rule, okay? There's some poor men out
there who need a bit of buffing up. But
for the most part, God designed men with
broader shoulders so that they could
bear heavy loads. God wants you to use
your strength, men, to be tough for her
and tender with her. You need to be
tough for her and tender with her.
You're getting an insight into how I
talk to the guys at Future Men.
Your wife needs to feel safe when she's
with you. She needs to know that you
love her. You protect her. Proverbs
29:11 says, "A fool gives full vent to
his spirits in the context of anger. A
fool gives full vent to his anger, but a
wise man quickly holds it back."
Proverbs 29:11. It's the fool who flies
off the handle. It's the fool who can't
control his emotions.
I don't think we realize, men, how
terrifying it is for women to submit to
a man that they don't trust. Does your
wife trust you? Does she feel safe
around you? that you love her. When a
woman marries a man, she's trusting him
that for the rest of her life, he will
not hurt her, hit her, harm her, wound
her, cut her, cheat on her. She's
trusting that he's going to work hard to
pay the bills, to love her children, to
love her children, to finish the race,
to walk with Christ. And when most
single women look around and survey the
land of eligible men, there's not much
hope for them, right? And I I agree with
that, especially with a culture that's
working against men, a culture that's
feminizing men or or talking about this
toxic masculinity, which again does
exist. Toxic masculinity is a thing, but
it's it's not the same thing as a
biblical masculinity. And so, husbands
in here need to alleviate fears of their
wives by living with them in an
understanding way, showing honor to
their wives as a weaker vessel because
that's how God loves his bride. That's
how God treats the church of the living
God. So what this means, men, going back
to first Peter 3, live with your wives
in an understanding way, literally
according to knowledge. In the Greek,
according to knowledge. Knowledge of
what? Knowledge of her. Knowledge of how
the Bible talks about her. It means
knowing what she loves and trying to do
that. And knowing what she hates and
trying not to do that. knowledge of her
and knowledge of how has God has
designed her. Which means you know what
she hates. It means you know what she
loves. That you connect with her on an
emotional level, not just sexually, but
emotionally. Your wife wants intimacy.
She wants relationship. She wants you to
show an interest in her needs. She wants
you to talk to her. It's funny. It says
dwell or live with your wives. It means
actually being with her, not on your
phone, not distracted, not doing other
things, right? Like focusing on what
she's saying, listening.
Now, the common objection you hear a lot
of men say is that, "Well, I just I'm
just not an emotional guy. I just I
don't connect with my emotions too well.
I'm I'm just too too manly, too tough,"
or whatever whatever excuse they use.
until you see them watching football or
playing golf or hunting or their team
scores a try, then then he's all full of
emotions, right? He's a very emotional
person. They even cry sometimes, men,
when their team wins.
All men have emotions. All women have
emotions. Both men and women are full of
emotions.
The difference is they express them in
masculine and feminine ways, but all men
and women have emotions because they're
made in God's image. So husbands need to
realize that women want an emotionally
stable man that controls his emotions
for her good and for his glory to
protect and to love her and to live with
her in a loving and understanding way.
That means men verbally you love her not
just physically but also verbally with
the words you use. Proverbs 15:1 a soft
answer turns away wrath. How many soft
answers are you giving to your wife? How
many soft replies are you giving to them
when an argument breaks out? You know
that there's those men out there that
say, "I could never hit a woman. I could
never physically assault a woman." But
they go on assaulting women with their
words, with their tongue. They hit them
with their tongues verbally, vocally.
They talk down to wives. They make them
feel weak, small, and insignificant.
There's a psalm that we quote regularly
in our house is Psalm 34:13.
Keep your tongue from evil. Keep your
tongue from evil. God hates evil
tongues. God hates men who talk down to
women who use their strength for evil,
not for good.
And so heavy is the head that wears the
crown. There's a great responsibility as
the head of the home. In Ephesians 5,
Paul lays down the principles for
husbands loving their wives. And he says
this, "Husbands, love your wives as
Christ loved the church and gave himself
up for her, that he might sanctify her,
having cleansed her by the washing of
the word, water with the word, so that
he might present the church to himself
in splendor without spot or wrinkle or
any such thing, that she might be holy
and without blemish." Notice Paul has
been reading Proverbs and he says what?
Christ died for the church to make the
church excellent,
to make her the excellent bride, to make
her the excellent wife, so that she
would be more and more conformed into
the image of that Proverbs 31 woman,
more holy, more like her savior.
Men, this is your duty. This is your
responsibility. You set the spiritual
climate of the home. You wash your word,
your children with with the word. You
wash your wife and your children with
the word.
And it's what Christ did, says Paul.
It's what Jesus does in the gospel. In
the gospel, there's a there's a
distinction made between fault and
responsibility. Right? Fault and
responsibility. 1 Corinthians 15, Christ
died for our sins according to the
scriptures. That's the essence of the
gospel. That's the good news. He died
for your sins. So that in the gospel,
Jesus becomes guilty for the sins that
were not his fault. They were his
responsibility. They were not his fault.
Is our sin Jesus Christ's fault? No. We
commit sin. We are the ones to blame.
We're the ones who crucified him and put
him on that cross with our sin. But did
Jesus take responsibility for that which
was not his fault? Absolutely. He took
full responsibility. He took our sins.
He bore our shame and our guilt because
he's the head of the church. And the
head takes responsibility for that which
is not his fault. And so husbands and
fathers, men in the home, although the
sins your wife commits, the sins your
children commit are not your fault, it
is your responsibility to assure and to
make sure that they're being dealt with.
Which means that a man doesn't save his
family. He's he doesn't save his family,
but he serves his family so that even
when it's not his fault, he makes sure
it's his responsibility. He makes sure
that confession of sin, that there's
repentance, that there's prayer at the
center of the marriage because that's
what Jesus does for his bride. This is
what true biblical marriage is and what
it looks like. And this is why marriage
can either be a great blessing and joy
or grief and pain. I'll finish with a
quote that I think's relevant to
marriage by CS Lewis. Um CS Lewis was
not a preacher, but he did preach from
time to time sermons. And one of his
most famous sermons that they turned
into a book was called The Weight of
Glory. The weight of glory. And in that
sermon, he talks about men and women who
are immortal souls. We're made in his
image and therefore we reflect his
immortal image. Men and women are people
who live forever. And so here's a
powerful image that he uses. I don't
know if that's a bit too small, but he
says, "It is a serious thing to live in
a society of possible gods and goddesses
and to remember that the dullst, most
uninteresting person you talk to may one
day be a creature which if you saw it
now, you would be strongly tempted to
worship or else a horror and corruption
that you meet only in a nightmare." All
day long we are in some degree helping
each other to one or the other of these
destinations. It is in the light of
these overwhelming possibilities that we
conduct all of our dealings with one
another or friendships, loves, play,
politics. There are no ordinary people.
You have never talked to a mere mortal.
nations, cultures, arts and
civilizations. These are mortal and
their life is to ours as the life of
anat. But it is mortals whom we joke
with, work with, marry, snub, and
exploit.
Immortal horrors or everlasting
joy.
joy. That's what's at stake.
in the covenant of marriage. Friend,
you have never lived in a home with a
mere mortal. That's true whether you're
married or not, but especially if you're
married, all day long you're helping
your spouse to one of two destinations:
Eternal glories
or eternal horrors.
God is making immortal souls in the
process of marriage, of family, of
parenting, of of wisdom, of
relationships.
The good news is that Jesus Christ is
the answer to all of our marital issues,
our personal sins and problems because
he came to make us more like his image
and his glory. And it begins by coming
to Christ and confessing our sins and
walking in the light of his glory and
grace. Whether you're a mother, whether
you're a father, whether you're a
husband, a wife, a son, a daughter,
married or single, children or no
children, Jesus Christ conforms you to
his image through the greatest marriage
this world will ever know, which is
Christ dying for sinners.
What a glorious reality and hope we have
both in this life in marriage and in the
marriage to come between Christ and the
church. Let's pray.
Our Lord and our God, we thank you for
your word.
We know that it is sometimes
sharp to our souls and it cuts it
pierces both bone and marrow, the the
marrow of the heart, Lord.
So, Father, I pray that you would shoot
those arrows of truth and conviction and
conversion and all the things that you
need for us to hear through the word of
God this morning, Lord. Father, I pray
for husbands who are not leading in
their homes that they would step up and
they would love their wives as Christ
loved the church. that they would lay
down their lives, lay down their selfish
habits and serve their wives and be holy
for their children and be holy for their
future children. Be holy for the sake of
you. I pray for wives as they [snorts]
seek to be godly
workers of the home and even those who
are working outside the home. I pray
that you would help them be more like
Jesus and more like the excellent woman
of Proverbs 31. Father, we all need your
grace in these areas. So, please build
us up and help us to be more like you in
every area of our lives. We ask and we
pray in Jesus name. Amen. And I'll
finish with um this reading from
Revelation 21. John writes, "Then I saw
a new heaven and a new earth, for the
first heaven and earth had passed away.
The sea was no more. And I saw the holy
city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of
heaven from God, prepared as a bride
adorned for her husband. And I heard a
loud voice from the throne, saying,
"Behold, the dwelling place of God is
with man. He will dwell with them, and
they will be his people. God himself
will be with them as their God, and he
will wipe away every tear from their
eyes. Death will be no more. Neither
shall there be mourning or crying or
pain anymore, for the former things have
passed away. Have a wonderful week
dwelling on your future home with God in
heaven.